RG 003, New London County Court Native Americans Collection
Connecticut State Library
One of the more interesting cases in the collection is Willard Hubbard v. Robert Cleland, concerning two whites from New London. The plaintiff, "School Master to the Indian Children of Mohegan," sued for £100 damages, claiming that Cleland published "false, feigned, Scandalous & libellous words & Expressions" against him for being unfit to be in charge of the school. The court heard the case in November 1772 and the papers contain one letter from Cleland to Andrew Oliver and the commissioners in Boston for "propagating Christian Knowledge amongst the Natives of this Land" and three to the Reverend David Jewett of New London North Society.50 The jury found the defendant guilty and ordered him to pay Hubbard £23-10 damages and court costs.51
In 1795, the New London County Court heard its first case under provision of "An Act for the Government and Regulation of Seamen in the Merchant's Service," passed by the Congress of the United States in July 1790, Edward Hallam, John Hallam, & Robert Hallam v. Willard alias William Miller of Stonington. Under contract to sail on a merchant voyage, Miller deserted before the ship left port and the plaintiffs sued. Lawyers for Miller pleaded for an abatement on the technicality that the writ was improper because he resided in Groton and had never lived in Stonington. Lawyers for the plaintiff responded by saying that Miller "has no fixed place of residence," because he "is one of the native Indians of this State & that the tribe to which he belongs [is] spread over the Towns of Stonington, Groton & Preston." The court agreed and Miller was told to pay £4-10 damages and £3-5-6 costs of suit.52
In one last example from Files giving a hint of the documentary riches found in the New London County Native Americans Collection, "Jeofry an Indian man of New London," along with five Rogerenes, was charged by the King's Attorney with profaning the Sabbath, specifically with disturbing church services on November 20, 1725. Jeofry and "divers other evil minded persons" did "in a very Rude and disorderly manner armed with a Club" disturbed the congregation. One of the group did "maliciously & basely misuse the preacher or Teacher of the sd. Congregation in an open and high handed manner." Jeofry or Jeffery petitioned the court, saying that he "was by a Corrupt and Evil mind[ed] [Person] prevailed Upon to Come into the... Congregation in New London" and "Humbly Crave yours honours pardon." He was fined twenty shillings.53
Additional information on Native Americans in southeastern Connecticut can be found in the Papers by Subject series of New London County Court Records. The collection contains thirty-eight new records and supplemental information on eighty-eight cases in Files. The new information comes primarily from four series - Costs (21), Miscellaneous (4), Revolutionary War Pensions (4), and Summons for Evidence (4). The bulk of the supplementary information is drawn from Costs and Executions.
Materials from Costs are divided between costs of lawsuits and those of imprisonment in the county jail. One example of the former is for costs of £2-11-7 recovered by Benjamin Uncas from John Story.54 The vast majority of costs, however, are those incurred by Native Americans sent to jail, for example, bills of $9.22 paid in November 1833 and $21.78 in March 1834 primarily for the board and clothes furnished Samuel Brushell.55 From the Miscellaneous series comes a document of a fine of £1-15 imposed upon Joseph Elderkin of Norwich in 1701 for "selling Drink to Indians."56 The four pensions granted to Native Americans includes one for sixty-three year old James Nedson of North Stonington who stated that he served in the Connecticut Line during the American Revolution, had little property, and had an aged wife and eleven children who depended upon him for support.57 The Summons for Evidence materials generally concern instances in which an Indian played a secondary role, as in Dom Rex v. Jonathan Richardson when an unidentified Indian was among three men identified as driving cattle from a field.58
Papers by Subject also includes additional material from eighty-eight lawsuits found in Files. The information generally comes from the Costs and Executions series. In June 1726, as an example, Ann Ruff of New London accused Moll, "an Indain [sic] Woman," of stealing cloth worth £11-13-5. Moll was found guilty, assessed £23-6-10 damages and court costs of £1-16-0, whipped 10 stripes on her naked back, and assigned to service because she was unable to pay the fine. Costs provide a detailed break down of costs, ones that include 6 shillings for the expense of the whipping.59 In another example, when John Johnson of Mohegan recovered judgment against Ephraim Wheeler for £1-1-8 debt and costs of suit £2-6-11, Costs again contains a detailed listing that includes expenses incurred by the plaintiff for costs taxed by the local j.p., for travel to the county court, for attendance, arbitration, attorney fees, and court fees.60 Executions hold the second substantial body of material to supplement Files. When Samuel Ward Esq. of Newport, Rhode Island recovered judgment against John and Margaret Tobee of Stonington, the writ of execution signed by county clerk Daniel Coit on November 26, 1766 directed that Tobee pay £4-0-9 debt and £2-0-9 costs of suit for a total of £6-1-6.61 In an execution for a criminal case, Jeremiah Shantup was sentenced to State Prison for eight years on the charge of manslaughter for killing Lodowick Wheeler.62
In thirty-seven cases, supplementary material is located in two series of Papers by Subject, usually Costs and Executions. In 1725, for example, Christopher Christophers recovered judgment against "Indian White Eyed Simon" for £2-9-1 debt and £1-2-3 costs and both in Costs and Executions contain new information.63
The New London County Native Americans Collection contains easily accessible information of great research value, much of which has not previously been examined by researchers.
Endnotes
2Sachem is considered a surname, as in Cesar Sachem, and so is Uncas.
3Apes (8), Ashbow/Ashpo (14), Cooper (17), George (4), Hoscote (12), Job (5), Ned/Nedson (4), Nonsuch (4), Occum (5), Sachem (10), Shantup (7), Shelley (9), Shon (4), Simons (8), Tantaquigeon (4), Uncas (35), and Waggs/Wyogs (6). Variations exist in the spelling of surnames.
4Mulatto is used in nineteen no surname cases in the New London Court African Americans Collection. Probably most had a mixture of Indian and Negro blood. The court records general\lly provide the racial identification upon which these figures are based, but racial identity becomes more difficult to determine in the eighteenth and nineteenth centuries dues to the extent of intermarriage between the two groups. It is possible, however, that someone who the court classes as a Negro may have Indian blood.
5Barbara W. Brown and James M. Rose, joint authors, Black Roots in Southeastern Connecticut, 1650-1900 (Detroit: Gale Research Co., 1980). Data was gathered and compiled from census, church, justice of the peace, land, pension, probate, town, and vital records, plus account books and some reference to the volumes of Trials in court records.
6The cases are found under a variety of subjects, including covenant broken, departed service, indenture, runaways, and sale of Indian servant.
7New London Court Native Americans Collection, Nov. 1714, Box 1, folder 6. The plaintiff withdrew the lawsuit.
8Nov. 1715, Box 1, folder 8. Both sides presented their cases to the court, but no evidence exists as to the disposition of the case.
9June 1739, Box 1, folder 39. The two attorneys argued that although Betty, a Pequot Indian, had surrendered herself to the colony government in 1676, she was never a slave because the legislature in October 1676 declared that all those surrendering could "not be Sold... for Slaves" and that Betty was only subject to service for ten years. See also, J. Hammond Trumbull, ed., The Public Records of the Colony of Connecticut, Vol. II (Hartford: F. A. Brown, 1852), 296-98.
10New London Court Native Americans Collection, June 1757, Box 2, folder 5. Indians were held at least temporarily as slaves in the following cases, John Winthrop v. William Walsworth, June 1721, Box 1, folder 18; John Winthrop v. William Walsworth, Nov. 1721, Box 1, folder 18; Daniel Lester v. Jonathan Rogers, June 1722, Box 1, folder 20; and Stephen Gardiner v. Cesar & others, Nov. 1743, Box 1, folder 44.
11June 1729, Box 1, folder 30.
12Both plaintiff and defendant: John Quequockum v. John Simon,June 1728, Box 1, folder 29; Samuel Uncas v. Ben Uncas, Nov. 1737, Box 1, folder 37; Rachell Robin v. Samuel Aspow, June J763, Box 2, folder 18; Henry Quoquid v. Zachary Johnson, Nov. 1766, Box 2, folder 26.
13Ibid, Feb. 1759, Box 2, folder 7. In a related case that was also withdrawn, Ishmael stated that he had served as mariner on board the privateer Defiance and that the was not paid his prize share of £40. Ibid, Feb. 1759, Box 2, folder 8.
14Feb. 1769, Box 2, folder 29.
15Passed in October 1724. Charles J. Hoadly, ed., The Public Records of the Colony of Connecticut Vol. VI (Hartford: Case, Lockwood & Brainard, 1872), 493. A later state law book provided the following language: "That no Judgment shall be rendered against and Indian for any Debt, or any Contract, except for Rents of Lands hired and occupied by such Indian." Acts and Laws of the State of Connecticut (Hartford: Hudson and Goodwin, 1796), 238.
16June 1768, Box 2, folder 28.
17June 1771, Box 2, folder 33.
18Benjamin Gray v. Jacob Hoscot, June 1766, Box 2, folder 23A. At the same session, Benjamin Gray v. Benjamin Uncas, in another suit for debt, the defendant defaulted and the plaintiff recovered £13-10-1. Ibid, Box 2, folder 23A.
19June 1774, Box 2, folder 37.
20Moses Warren v. William L. Paine and James Powers, Mar. 1826, Box 3, folder 17; Jedediah R. Gay v. John G. Fitch, "overseer of the Mohegan tribe of Indians. Nov. 1840, Box 3, folder 24.
21Samuel Ashbow v. Samuel Bolls, June 1782, Box 2, folder 38.
22Samuel Chesebrough, 2d v. Samuel Shelley, June 1799, Box 3, folder 2. Found in no docket cases.
23George Chebuck v. Simon Quocheats, Ibid, Nov. 1768, Box 2, folder 28.
24Nov. 1727, Box 1, folder 29.
25Nov. 1731, Box 1, folder 31.
26June 1738, Box 1, folder 38.
27Nov. 1766, Box 2, folder 25.
28Hannah Brushell v. Lemuel Brushell, June 1815, Box 3, folder 10; Lucy Brushell v. Perygreen Wheeler & Topliff Wheeler, June 1815, Box 3, folder 11.
29State v. Gershom Calvin, June 1825, Box 3, folder 16; State v. Samuel Ingraham & Nathaniel Tracy, June 1825, Box 3, folder 17.
30Apr. 1703, Box 1, folder 1.
31Nov. 1771, Box 2, folder 34.
32Nov. 1712, Box 1, folder 4.
33State v. William Apes, June 1815, Box 3, folder 11.
34Not included here are a series of early eighteenth-century lawsuits over control over the Quinebaug lands, then in New London County, but after 1726 in Windham County. For information on this subject, see Richard L. Bushman, From Puritan to Yankee: Character and the Social Order in Connecticut, 1690-1765 (Cambridge, Mass.: Harvard University Press, 1967), 84-103.
35Nov. 1722, Box 1, folder 22.
36June 1757, Box 2, folder 5. This case is particularly noteworthy because it gives the names of most, if not all, of the adult male members of the tribe. Another lawsuit the next year provided a similar listing of tribal members. Feb. 1758, Box 2, folder 6.
37Simeon Miner v. Nathaniel Brown, Nov. 1762, Box 2, folder 17; Miner v. Jacob Park, Nov. 1762, Box 2, folder 17; Miner v. John Perkins, June 1763, Box 2, folder 20; Miner v. Sherebiah Tracy, Feb. 1764, Box 2, folder 20; Miner v. Sherebiah Tracy, Feb. 1758, Box 2, folder 28; Miner v. Silas Deane, June 1771, Box 2, folder 33.
38Ezekiel M. Cooper Petition, Sep. 1849, Box 3, folder 27.
39Charles D. Boheme, etc. v. Charles H. Cooper ,etc., Feb. 1785, Box 3, folder 28. The case was erased from the records of the court.
40Feb. 1769, Box 2, folder 30.
41Nov. 1769, Box 2, folder 32.
42June 1784, Box 2, folder 41.
43Nov. 1733, Box 1, folder 34; June 1734, Box 1, folder 34.
44William Roe Miner v. Capt. John Stanton, Feb. 1762, Box 2, folders 14-15. In the other case, Benjamin Hubbard v. Abell Moor, the plaintiff, "(Indian Man) of Lyme," sued to collect teamster wages for "driving the Kings Teams" in 1760. June 1762, box 2, folder 16.
45June 1771, Box 2, folder 33.
46June 1757, Box 2, folder 5.
47Nov. 1761, Box 2, folder 14. The General Court first passed legislation prohibiting the sale of alcoholic beverages to Native Americans in April 1654. James Hammond Trumbull, The Public Records of the Colony of Connecticut, Vol. I (Hartford: Brown & Parsons, 1850), 254-55.
48Nathaniel Post v. Joshua Abell, Nov. 1751, Box 2, folder 1; State v. Mark D. Brown, June 1846, Box 3, folder 26.
49Nov. 1823, Box 3, folder 15.
50The formal name of the organization was the Massachusetts Society for Propagating Christian Knowledge among the Indians of North America. Clifford K. Shipton, Sibley's Harvard Graduates; Biographical Sketches of those who Attended Harvard College, Vol. 7 (Boston: Massachusetts Historical Society, 1945), 387.
51Nov. 1772, Box 2, folder 35.
52June 1795, Box 3, folder 1.
53Nov. 1725, Box 1, folder 26.
54Nov. 1767, Box 4, folder 20.
55Nov. 1833, Mar. 1834, Box 4, folder 23.
56Miscellaneous, 1701, Box 4, folder 47.
57Pensions, June 1820, Box 4, folder 48.
58Summons for Evidence, June 1741, Box 4, folder 53.
59Dom Rex v. Moll, June 1726, Box 1, folder 27; NLCC Trials, Vol. 15, 206; Costs, June 1726, Box 4, folder 7.
60John Johnson v. Ephraim Wheeler, Nov. 1759, Box 2, folder 9; Costs, Nov. 1759, Box 4, folder 17.
61Samuel Ward v. John Tobee & Margaret his Wife, Nov. 1766, Box 4, folder 44.
62State v. Jermiah Shantup, Sep. 1835, Box 4, folder 45.
63Christopher Christophers v. White Eyed Simon, Feb. 1725, Box 4, folder 6; Box 4, folder 36.
Related Material
Related information can be found in Dockets and in Trials, particularly for the period up to about 1720, and Superior Court Records.
Database of Cases
A database of records to the 396 cases involving Native Americans has been created. It contains fields for surname, first name, residence, date of court session, case name, subject, and tribe. It can be accessed by researchers from the Connecticut State Library website at:.
Index Terms
Organizations:
Connecticut. County Court (New London County)
Subjects:
County courts -- Connecticut -- New London County -- History; Indians of North America -- Connecticut -- History -- 18th century; Connecticut. County Court (New London County) -- History; Connecticut. Judicial Dept. -- History; Connecticut -- History -- Sources; New London County Native Americans Collection
Document Types:
Civil court records; Criminal Court records; Judicial records
Restrictions on Access
This artificial collection of materials on Native Americans found in Files and Papers by Subject of the New London County Court consists of photocopies of original documents. All originals have been restricted.
See the policy.
Provenance
The New London Court Native Americans Collection, consisting solely of photocopies of documents on cases involving Indians, was created to provide easier access to those researchers primarily interested in the history of these individuals and tribes.
Container List
- 1. Files
  - 1698 - 1750 (Box 1, Folder 1-45)
  - 1751 - 1774 (Box 2, Folder 1-37)
  - 1782 - 1789 (Box 2, Folder 38-44)
  - 1793 - 1855 (Box 3, Folder 1-33)
- 2. Papers by Subject
  - Conservators and Guardians, 1820 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Costs, 1716 - 1850 (Box 4, Folder 1-30)
  - Court Expenses, 1731 - 1840 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Executions, 1716 - 1845 (Box 4, Folder 31-46)
  - Inquests, 1786 (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - Miscellaneous, 1706 - 1720 (Box 4, Folder 46-47)
  - Pensions, 1820 (Box 4, Folder 48-49)
  - Summons for Evidence, 1712 - 1767 (Box 4, Folder 49-54)